我想开始谈论功能或
I wanna start off talking about function or
Mona Transformers 通过谈论函子组合。
Mona Transformers by talking about functor composition.
所以我们这里有一个表示 compose 的类型。
So what we have here is a type that says compose.
我要买另外两种 F 型和 G 型，然后我会给你一个新的 M 型。
I'm gonna take two other types F and G and I'm gonna return you a new type M.
如果我想在 M 中放一些东西，我们会将它放在 G、F 和 M 中。
And if I wanna put something in M, we'll put it in the G, in the F, and in the M.
如果我想映射，我会映射到 g，然后映射到 f，
And if I wanna map, I'll map over the g, and map over the f,
并将其保存在 M 中。
and keep that in the M.
酷，好吧，让我们看看这是如何工作的。
Cool, all right, let's see how this works.
我可以说，好吧，我让我们称之为 TaskEither。
I can say, well, I have let's call a TaskEither.
我会作曲。
And I'll make a compose.
我会撰写（任务，要么），好吗？
And I'll Compose(Task, Either), okay?
我想在 TaskEither 中放入一些东西。
I wanna put something in a TaskEither.
因此，无论是在内部还是外部，这都是一项任务。
So it's a task on the outside either on the inside.
那就对了。
That's right.
那么我们会说 TaskEither of, to。
So then we'll say TaskEither of, to.
给自己一些空间将映射到我们有一到两次，
Give myself some space will map over that we have a to two times,
10 将再次映射它，只是为了有趣的 2 或这个 10 20。
10 will map over it again just for funsies two or this 10 20.
[笑] 天哪。
[LAUGH] Goodness.
所以我们得到了 20 &lt;&gt; 20 + 1。
So we got twenty &lt;&gt; twenty + 1.
好的，然后我们要分叉这个，因为这也不是一项任务。
All right, and then we're going to fork this, because it is not a task either.
它是 TaskEither 的组合。
It's a compose of TaskEither.
所以我们实际上必须把它从组合中取出来。
So we actually have to get it out of the the compose.
现在我已经展示了几次提取物。
Now I've shown extract a few times.
对于你们这些新折叠之类的人，提取物来自，
And for those of you who new fold and such, extract is coming from,
它不接受函数，然后将其传递给函数。
it does not take the function and then pass that to the function.
你把它拿出来，它是普通广告的一部分
You just get it out and it's part of the common ad
界面，但这只是其中的一部分。
interface, but it's only one piece of that.
好的，所以我们可以从 compose 中提取出我们的 TaskEither。
Okay, so we can extract out of the compose to get our TaskEither.
一旦我们调用这个 console.error 然后我们在那里得到两者之一，
And once we call this console.error and then we get the either in there,
然后我们可以将两者之一折叠到 console.log，console.log。
then we could fold out the either to a console.log, console.log.
不错，棒棒哒
All right, terrific.
人们看到这是如何运作的。
People see how this is working.
我的任务之一是映射其中的值，并且
I have a task of either of mapping over the value inside of it and
从撰写中取出。
to take out of the compose.
所以我得到了我的任务，然后我运行了它，并且任务被持有，所以
So I get my task, and then I run that, and the task is holding either, so
然后我得到我的。
then I get my either.
但在我的整个计算过程中，
But during my whole computation,
我真的不必在意，我不必在整个地方都绘制地图。
I didn't really have to care, I didn't have to map map all over the place.
我的一张地图只为我做了两张地图。
My one map just did both maps for me.
所以如果我运行它transformers/0，我们得到21，完美。
So if I run it transformers/0, we got 21, perfect.
所以函子可以毫不费力地组合起来。
And so functors compose effortlessly.
任何函子都只是与其他人组合。
Any functor just composes with others.
事实上，你可以用 compose 来组合它，
In fact, you can compose it with compose,
我可以说我可以用那个组合身份等等，它是关联的。
I could say I could compose identity with that and so on, and it's associative.
我们实际上有一个恒等函子，不是吗？
And we actually have an identity functor don't we?
所以实际上函子本身用于形式类别，它们的作用类似于函数。
So actually functors themselves for form category where they act like functions.
你可以组合它们并且你有一个身份和
You can compose them and you have an identity and
然后他们提供了这种从功能中一键点击的功能。
then they provide this whole kind of one click up from functions.
这是一个完整的合成工具包。
It's a whole composition toolkit.
但我们不会走得太远，事情会变得棘手。
But we're not gonna go too far into it, where things get hairy.
如果我确实链接，我必须以某种方式提供一个 TaskEither。
If I do chain I have to somehow provide a TaskEither.
所以我也进入了这个
So I get into this too and
我必须处理创建另一个任务来链接它。
I have to deal with creating another task either to chain that.
这不是机械的。
And that is not mechanical.
这并不总是奏效。
That doesn't always work.
你不能只写两个 mon 广告。
You can't just compose two mon ads.
并期待它为我们连锁。
And just expect it to chain for us.
我们不能在这里写一个有意义的链，在 compose 中。
We can't write a chain that makes sense here, in compose.
每个人都明白这个事实吗，也许不是为什么，但至少
Does everybody understand that fact, maybe not why but at least
有一个事实说我们不能在这里写一个平面地图或一个链。
there's a fact that says we cannot write a flat map or a chain in here.
我们对每一种蒙泰克，每一种类型都有意义
And we make sense like for each montaic, kind of each type
如果您不符合类型，则有自己的方式来指定地图和链。
has its own way to specify map and chain if you're gonna fall out of the type.
你必须知道细节，这就是你的
You have to know about the details and this you just it just
立即为您备份，这样您就可以随时映射地图，一切都很好。
bottles it right back up for you so you can always map map and you're fine.
所以我们不能把这些东西串联起来。
So we cannot chain these these things.
那我们该怎么办？
So what are we gonna do?
我们看到我们可以，我们可以将任务组合成一个幺半群和
We saw we could, we can kind of combine task and either into a monoid and
只是说喜欢，我只是要继续结合我的地图我的任务食者和
just say like, I'm just gonna keep combining my map my task eaters and
通过串联处理其中的内容。
work with the stuff inside it through concatenation.
但通常你会想要映射和链接，所以你可以运行
But typically you're going to want to map and chain, so you could run
其上的功能组合，而不仅仅是结合他们的见解。
a composition of functions over it instead of just combining their insights.